Yeah.
So thank you very much,
everyone, for coming.
Yeah, that's the title of my presentation.
I guess I'll just jump right into it.
So just a preface,
but this is a working chapter.
It's part of my upcoming thesis.
So I do feel like some of my stuff
is sort of half-baked.
So I welcome any suggestions
and reading recommendations
that anyone feels like
is relevant to my project.
And if anyone has read my abstract,
I just want to say that like,
some stuff has changed
since I submitted the original abstract.
So I hope it's not too bewildering,
but I've just added some—
like an additional concept
to the theoretical framework. So
from the title,
I want to start off
by introducing melancholy.
So in more recent history,
I think everyone might
or might not be familiar.
Melancholy has sort of been construed
as an illness to be cured.
Sigmund Freud specifically theorized it
as a kind of mourning
that has gone wrong,
where the subject is unable to detach,
so to speak, from the lost object,
which manifests as
these symptoms right here,
like a loss of interest
in the outside world and inhibition
of any kind of performance,
and a self-hate and self-flagellation.
And how is this— why is this important?
It's because
politically— sorry.
Melancholy has sort of come
to characterize
our historical moment
after the collapse of the Soviet Union—the
USSR—there seemed for a long time
a lack of a capitalist alternative, i.e.
neoliberal— liberalism
seemed to have won the ideological battle.
We see this from Francis Fukuyama’s
“end of history,”
this quote from Furey
and this from Fredric Jameson right here,
that encapsulate this sense of finality
with respect to, like, our politics.
And Wendy Brown more specifically targets
the intellectual or the Western left.
For Wendy Brown, they identify these
finalized sort of narratives as having
a sort of dispiriting effect on the left
and, by extension, the collective impetus
to think outside of capital.
For Wendy Brown,
who was writing in 1999,
the left she saw was paralyzed
by this sense of melancholy.
They became more preoccupied
with mourning their loss
and with regrouping
and investing in political change.
On the contrary, more recently, other
theorists like Jonathan Flatley, pictured
here, have begun to think melancholy
as something that can be more productive.
Jonathan Flatley, for one, conceives
of it as melancholizing
as a kind of method, and this falls
under his larger framework of affective
mapping, which, in his words, names
a particular set of aesthetic strategies
that allow one to perceive the historicity
of one's affective experience.
His idea of mapping
takes some inspiration from
Fredric
Jameson, who talked about cognitive
mapping
as a way of exercising
or like finding political agency.
I thought the idea of cognitive mapping
was best summarized
in this quote here, where he compares
cognitive mapping to physical mapping.
For Jameson, therefore, the inability
to situate oneself vis-à-vis
society
and history is as debilitating to politics
as not having a map for reference
is to navigating urban spaces.
So going back to Flatley.
I read Flatley’s reading of Jameson
and his idea of affective mapping
as saying one's
writing of melancholy—because
he was mainly working with literary texts
here—is a way of making sense
of a certain experience
and then sharing that sense-making
with the reader, and this framework
then guides the reader in the future.
To put it simply,
it provides a sort of location
of this melancholy affect in relation—
and puts it in relation
to the historical moment and beyond.
This brings me to
the idea of melancholic agency,
as Flatley himself
says, with reference to Jameson's idea
of cognitive mapping:
just as one needs a cognitive map
of city space in order to have
a sense of agency in that space, one
requires a cognitive map of social space
for a sense of agency in the world
more generally or politically.
This dovetails
nicely with Brigid Bargetz’s
borrowing the title of Donna
Haraway, “Staying with the Trouble,”
suggests that we must stay
with the melancholy in order to remain
attuned with the political struggles
of the past, and hence to the larger
picture of the leftist project, which is,
you know, to forward social change.
In other words,
to go back to Wendy's Brown,
Wendy Brown's charge of left melancholy
as a thing of paralysis.
Bargetz is saying perhaps some of this
melancholy is productive, or in some ways
necessary
for the future of anti-capitalism.
So how does this relate to video games
and electronic literature?
I'm kind of,
I suppose, seeking to build on
Flatley's idea of affective mapping,
since his work mainly
deals in modernist literature
and therefore more textual in the old
sense of the medium.
I ask, how do video games,
as an aesthetic form,
channel these emancipatory desires?
How do they render
the post-capitalist imaginary
and therefore act as an affective map
for this resistive struggle
alongside other art forms like literature?
I think as all of us
at this electronic literature
conference can agree,
there are many similarities
between video games and literature,
so I hope the connection
isn't too crazy to make.
But in many ways,
I feel like video games as a new art form
borrows from and adapts
from the literature of old.
Firstly, video games are quite
literally narrative worlds,
and in some sense again
borrows from the old,
but also uses a new set
of aesthetic strategies
to build an aesthetic effect—
affective map, so to speak,
and also, and more obviously,
virtual space sort of lends itself
to the idea of mapping,
and I kind of would like to explore that
sort of connection,
like how does a physical
or rather like more literal space function
as an affective map?
Over here,
I thought Henry Jenkins’ “Narrative
Architecture and Embedded
Narratives” would be instructive.
But for the interest of time,
I won't go too into that.
And onto Disco Elysium.
It's one of my key texts
that I will be examining for my thesis,
and to answer those earlier questions,
and to deepen this discussion.
I will elaborate on it in a bit.
But before that,
for those that aren't familiar
with the game, it is a roleplaying,
point-and-click adventure game
that follows the troubled
detective pictured here on the right,
who, after some drug and alcohol binge,
has forgotten his identity.
But he's been tasked with investigating
a murder that happened in the district
of Martinaise, a fictional district
which is a sort of backwater neighborhood
that, in the not-so-distant past,
had been embroiled in a revolutionary war
fought between the communists
and an international neoliberal
governing body,
which ultimately resulted
in the communists’ defeat.
This murder—
You know, this sets the background
of the murder, because the murder involves
the hanging of a mercenary,
which was hired by a big shipping company
operating out of Martinaise
by the local trade union
paying this mercenary.
And through this investigation,
the player
sort of pieces together
the story and and the narrative world,
but also the protagonist's own identity,
because he's sort of in a fugue state.
So the player gets to know
a lot about the history,
but also the character.
And these things
sort of intertwine at a certain point.
And gameplay wise,
Disco Elysium features very little combat
and is modeled after tabletop
RPG games, where events are resolved
through skill checks, i.e.
a series of dice rolls.
And you can see
in this sort of screenshot
here, you have to roll a certain number
to pass the check,
and therefore to proceed
like successfully or
results in a failure.
And dialog trees are,
you know, explored
using a system of 24 skills
representing the protagonist's
different aspects
and personalities,
each of whom can speak directly
to our detective here,
aka our player— Sorry.
And therefore influence their decision
making throughout the story.
So what does Disco Elysium
add specifically to this discussion,
and how does it exemplify
the concept of affective
mapping and melancholic agency?
Evidently, I feel like Disco
Elysium is quite politically charged
and tells a rather melancholic
set of nested narratives.
What, with the drunken detective
and failed revolution
on the part of the communists,
which mirrors our own.
And this melancholy is reflected
in the landscape, in its bleak setting,
and also the gameplay mechanics,
or rather lack thereof.
On the latter point,
on gameplay mechanics, offers
the most differentiation,
I think, to traditional literature, and
so I'll try to spend some time
elaborating on it in the interest of time.
Disco Elysium
is, I think, for the conventional gamer,
a boring game because there's nothing
much really happens.
There's no combat
and no mechanical difficulty.
You don't have to defeat any bosses
by like pressing the right buttons
at the right time, and the player
isn't really afforded much agency
compared to your usual open world games,
like defeating of enemies,
you can't really roam around a big open
world.
There's no dramatic power scaling, etc.
and I read this lack,
so to speak, as both reflective
and evocative of that melancholic affect.
The gameplay, in effect, attempts
to capture a sense of ennui and loss
suffusing ordinary life,
while also telling a story
that contextualizes these effects
in relation to revolutionary loss.
To give a brief example, I think I'm
definitely running out of time, but
the game sort of acclimatizes the player
to failure through the skill checks.
It's very unlikely
that you pass every skill check
and sometimes you find yourself
failing them.
And as players, we've often been trained
to react negatively to failure.
But in Disco Elysium, failures
sometimes give you sort of funny outcomes.
For instance, in the opening of the game,
there's a check where if the player fails,
you flip off an NPC character
while running backwards, and then you
crash into a woman in a wheelchair.
And it's really funny, as opposed
to just running away successfully.
And the former, apart from being,
you know, kind of funny,
also opens up a lot more dialog options
with the surrounding NPCs
who never would have said certain things
if the player hadn't failed to check.
And so this affective response
from the player
initially might be disappointment
and in some sense like a sense of loss,
but they are soon attuned
to the alternative possibilities
and pathways
that are attached to this failure.
And combined with the overarching sort
of political narrative of the game,
one can sort of see the gameplay as a sort
of mapping of failure and melancholy
to pathways of possibilities,
and in turn providing the player
with an affective guide, so to speak,
for how their emotions and desire
can be channeled,
reoriented, and remapped.
And we're coming
to the end of the presentation, I swear.
But here is where I have some unanswered
questions that perhaps— like
if the audience has any responses,
feel free.
But I think I'm having trouble making
sense of the ambivalence of melancholy,
because I think it's clear that
melancholy is not inherently resistive.
It's not inherently
revolutionary.
You can also be used for conservative
or reactionary purposes, as we've seen in
the left melancholy and therefore like,
how do I make sense of this ambivalence?
Is there a way to attune ourselves
to the more emancipatory strands of it?
And if anyone is familiar with the game,
are there any other gameplay features
that might be missing
or should pay more attention to?
And with that, thank you so much
for paying attention and for being here.
And I've come to
the end of my presentation.